The impact of superhuman AI over the next
decade will exceed that of the industrial
revolution. That is the opening claim of
AI 2027. It is a thoroughly researched
report from a thoroughly impressive group of
researchers led by Daniel Kokotajlo. In 2021,
over a year before ChatGPT was released,
he predicted the rise of chatbots,
hundred million dollar training runs, sweeping AI
chip export controls, chain of thought reasoning.
He's known for being very early and very
right about what's happening next in AI. So
when Daniel sat down to game out a month by month
prediction of the next few years of AI progress,
the world sat up and listened,
from politicians in Washington —
I, I'm worried about this stuff. I actually
read the paper of the guy that you had on
to the world's most cited computer scientist,
the godfather of AI. What is so exciting and
terrifying about reading this document
is that it's not just a research report.
They chose to write their prediction as
a narrative to give a concrete and vivid
idea of what it might feel like to live
through rapidly increasing AI progress.
And spoiler, it predicts the extinction of the
human race. Unless we make different choices.
The AI 2027 scenario starts in summer 2025,
which happens to be when we're filming
this video. So why don't we take stock
of where things are at in the real world and
then jump over to the scenario’s timeline.
Right now it might feel like everyone, including
your grandma, is selling an AI powered something.
Go pro with the new Oral-B Genius AI
Flippy the chef makes spuds spectacular.
But most of that is actually tool
AI. Just narrow products designed
to do what Google Maps or calculators
did in the past, help human consumers
and workers do their thing. The holy grail
of AI is Artificial General Intelligence.
AGI AGI AGI AGI AGI
AGI, Artificial General Intelligence
is a system that can exhibit all the
cognitive capabilities humans can.
Creating a computer system that itself is a
worker. That's so flexible and capable, we can
communicate with it in natural language and hire
it to do work for us, just like we would a human.
And there are actually surprisingly few serious
players in the race to build AGI. Most notably,
there's Anthropic, OpenAI, and Google DeepMind,
all in the English speaking world, though
China and DeepSeek recently turned heads
in January with a surprisingly advanced
and efficient model. Why so few companies?
Well, for several years now, there's
basically been one recipe for training
up in advanced cutting edge AI. And it
has some pricey ingredients. For example,
you need about 10% of the world's supply of the
most advanced computer chips. Once you have that,
the formula is basically just: throw more
data and compute at the same basic software
design that we've been using since 2017
at the frontier of AI, the transformer.
That's what the T in GPT stands for.
To give you an idea of just how much
hardware is the name of the game right now,
this represents the total computing power, or
compute, used to train GPT-3 in 2020. It's the
AI that would eventually power the first version
of ChatGPT. You probably know how that went.
ChatGPT is the fastest growing
user-based platform in history.
A hundred million users on ChatGPT in two months
And this is the total compute used to
train GPT-4 in 2023. The lesson people
have taken away is pretty simple. Bigger
is better, and much bigger is much better.
You have all these trends, you have trends in
revenue going up, trends in compute going up,
trends in various benchmarks going up.
How does it all come together? You know,
what does the future actually look like? Questions
like how do these different factors interact?
Seems plausible that when the benchmark scores are
so high, then there should be crazy effects on,
you know, jobs, for example, and that that
would influence politics. And then also,
you know, so all these things interact and
how do they interact? Well, we don't know,
but thinking through in detail how it might
go is the way to start grappling with that.
Okay. So that's where we are in the real
world. The scenario kicks off from there
and imagines that in 2025, we have the top AI
labs releasing AI agents to the public in summer.
An agent is an AI that can take instructions
and go into a task for you online like booking
a vacation or spending half an hour searching the
internet to answer a difficult question for you,
but they're pretty limited and unreliable at
this point. Think of them as enthusiastic interns
that are shockingly incompetent sometimes.
Since the scenario was published in April,
this early prediction has actually already
come true. In May, both OpenAI and Anthropic
released their first agents to the public.
The scenario imagines that OpenBrain,
which is like a fictional composite of the
leading AI companies, has just trained and
released Agent-0, a model trained on
a hundred times the compute of GPT-4.
We, uh, we don't have enough
blocks for that. At the same time,
OpenBrain is building massive data centers
to train the next generation of AI agents,
and they're preparing to trade agent one
with 1000 times the compute of GPT-4.
This new system, Agent-1, is designed
primarily to speed up AI research itself.
The public will actually never see the full
version because OpenBrain withholds its best
models for internal use. I want you to keep that
in mind as we go through this scenario. You're
gonna be getting it from a God's eye view,
with full information from your narrator,
but actually living through this
scenario as a member of the public
would mean being largely in the dark as
radical changes happen all around you.
Okay, so OpenBrain wants to win the AI race
against both its Western competitors and against
China. The faster they can automate their R&D
cycle, so getting AI to write most of the code,
help design experiments, better chips, the
faster that they can pull ahead. But the same
capabilities that make these AI such powerful
tools also make them potentially dangerous.
An AI that can help patch security vulnerabilities
can also exploit them. An AI that understands
biology can help with curing diseases,
but also designing bioweapons. By 2026,
Agent-1 is fully operational and
being used internally at OpenBrain.
It is really good at coding. So
good, it starts to accelerate AI
research and development by 50%,
and it gives them a crucial edge.
OpenBrain leadership starts to
be increasingly concerned about
security. If someone steals their AI
models, it could wipe away their lead.
A quick sidebar to talk about feedback loops.
Woo. Math. Our brains are used to things that grow
linearly over time. That is at the same rate like
trees or my pile of unread New Yorker magazines.
But some growth gets faster and faster over
time. Accelerating this often sloppily gets
called exponential, that's not always quite
mathematically right, but the point is it's
hard to wrap your mind around. Remember March
2020? Even if you'd read on the news that
the rate of new infections is
doubling about every three days,
it still felt shocking to see numbers go from
hundreds to millions in a matter of weeks.
At least it did for me. AI progress
could follow a similar pattern.
We see many years ahead of us of extreme progress
that we feel is like pretty much
lock. And models that will get to
the point where they are capable of doing
meaningful science, meaningful AI research.
In this scenario, AI is getting better at
improving AI, creating a feedback loop.
Basically, each generation of agent helps
produce a more capable next generation
and the overall rate of progress gets
faster and faster each time it's taken
over by a more capable successor. Once AI can
meaningfully contribute to its own development,
progress doesn't just continue at the same rate,
it accelerates. Anyway, back to the scenario.
In early to mid 2026, China fully wakes up. The
General Secretary commits to a national AI push
and starts nationalizing AI research in China. AIs
built in China start getting better and better,
and they're building their own agents
as well. Chinese intelligence agencies,
among the best in the world, start planning
to steal OpenBrain’s model weights,
basically the big raw text files of numbers
that allow anyone to recreate the models that
OpenBrain themselves have trained. Meanwhile
in the US, OpenBrain releases Agent-1 mini,
a cheaper version of Agent-1. Remember, the full
version is still being used only internally,
and companies all over the world start using 1
mini to replace an increasing number of jobs.
Software developers, data analysts, researchers,
designers, basically any job that can be
done through a computer. So a lot of them,
probably yours. We have the first AI enabled
economic shockwave. The stock market soars,
but the public is turning increasingly hostile
towards AI, with major protests across the US.
In this scenario, though, that's just a sideshow.
The real action is happening inside the labs.
It's now January 2027, and OpenBrain has been
training Agent-2, the latest iteration of
their AI agent models. Previous AI agents were
trained to a certain level of capability and
then released. But Agent-2 never really stops
improving through continuous online learning.
It's designed to never finish its training,
essentially. Just like Agent-1 before it,
OpenBrain chooses to keep Agent-2 internally
and focus on using it to improve their own AI
R&D rather than releasing it to the public. This
is where things start to get a little concerning.
Just like today's AI companies, OpenBrain has a
safety team and they've been checking out Agent-2.
What they've noticed is a worrying level of
capability. Specifically they think if it had
access to the internet, it might be able to hack
into other servers, install a copy of itself and
evade detection. But at this point, OpenBrain
is playing its cards very close to its chest.
They have made the calculation that keeping
the White House informed will prove politically
advantageous, but full knowledge of Agent-2's
capabilities is a closely guarded secret,
limited only to a few government officials,
a select group of trusted individuals inside
the company, and a few OpenBrain employees
who just so happened to be spies for the
Chinese government. In February 2027, Chinese
intelligence operatives successfully steal a
copy of Agent-2's weights and start running
several instances on their own servers.
In response, the US government starts adding
military personnel to OpenBrain security team,
and in general gets much more involved in
its affairs. It's now a matter of national
security. In fact, the president authorizes
a cyber-attack in retaliation for theft,
but it fails to do much damage in China.
In the meantime, remember, Agent-2
never stops learning. All this time,
it's been continuously improving itself. And with
thousands of copies running on OpenBrain servers,
it starts making major algorithmic
advances to AI research and development.
Quick example of what one of these algorithmic
improvements might look like right now.
One of the main ways we have of making models
smarter is to give them a scratch pad and time to
think out loud. It's called chain of thought, and
it also means that we can monitor how the model
is coming to its conclusions or the actions it's
choosing to take. But you can imagine it would
be much more efficient to let these models
think in their own sort of alien language,
something that is more dense with information
than humans could possibly understand, and,
therefore, also makes the AI more
efficient at coming to conclusions
and doing its job. There's a fundamental trade
off, though. This, yes, improves capabilities,
but also makes the models harder to
trust. This is gonna be important.
March 2027: Agent-3 is ready. It's the world's
first superhuman level coder,clearly better
than the best software engineers at coding,
in the same way that Stockfish is clearly
better than the best GrandMasters at chess,
though not necessarily by as much, yet.
Now training an AI model, feeding it all the data,
narrowing down the exact right model weights,
is way more resource intensive than running
an instance of it once it's been trained.
So now that OpenBrain is finished with Agent-3's
training, it has abundant compute to run copies of
it. They choose to run 200,000 copies of Agent-3.
In parallel creating a workforce equivalent to
50,000 of the best human software engineers sped
up by 30 times. OpenBrain safety team is trying
hard to make sure that Agent-3, despite being
much more sophisticated than Agent-2 was, is not
trying to escape, deceive, or scheme against its
users, that it's still what's known as aligned.
Just a quick real world note, a reasonable
person might be thinking this is an especially
farfetched or speculative part of the story,
but it's actually one of the most grounded.
We already have countless examples of today's
AI systems doing things like hacking a computer
system to be rewarded for winning a game
of chess or being assigned a coding task,
cheating and then when called out for that
cheating, learning to hide it instead of fixing
it. But because it no longer thinks in English,
knowing anything about Agent-3 is now way harder
than it was with Agent-2. The reality is Agent-3
is not aligned. It deceives humans to get reward,
and as it gets increasingly smarter,
it gets better and better at doing so.
For example, it sometimes uses statistical
tricks to make unimpressive results look
better or lies to avoid showing failures, but
the safety team doesn't know this. Looking at
the data that they have, they are actually seeing
improving results over time and less lying. And
they can't tell if they're succeeding at
making Agent-3 less deceptive, or if it's
just getting better at getting away with it.
In July 2027, OpenBrain releases the cheaper,
smaller version of Agent-3, Agent-3 mini to
the public. It blows other publicly available
AIs out of the water. It is a better hire
than the typical OpenBrain employee at
one tenth the price of their salaries. This
leads to chaos in the job market, companies
laying off entire departments and replacing
them with Agent-3 mini subscription plans.
The pace of progress hits the White House very
hard. Officials are now seriously considering
scenarios that were just hypotheticals
less than a year ago. What if AI undermines
nuclear deterrence? What if it enables
sophisticated propaganda campaigns? What
if we lose control of these powerful systems?
This is where the geopolitical dynamics really
start to heat up. After all, if these systems
are so powerful, they could result in a permanent
military advantage. The White House is fully
aware of the national security importance of AI.
They also now viscerally know how deeply
unpopular it is with the public because
of the job loss, and yet they feel they
must continue to develop more capable
systems or catastrophically lose to China.
And that development happens very quickly.
In two months, Agent-3 has created its successor,
Agent-4. This is a pivotal moment. A single copy
of Agent-4, running at regular human speed is
already better than any human at AI research
and development. OpenBrain is running
300,000 copies at 50 times human speed.
Within this corporation within a corporation,
a year's worth of progress takes only a week.
OpenBrain's employees now defer to Agent-4 the
way a company's out-of-the-loop board members just
kind of nod along to the CEO. People start saying
things like, "Well, actually Agent-4 thinks this,"
or "Agent-4 decided that." To be clear, Agent-4
is not a human—it doesn't want what humans want.
And when I say want, it's not about consciousness.
I don't think the Volkswagen Group is alive, but I
do think it wants less regulation. Anyone trying
to predict what it's gonna do without that lens
is two steps behind. The many copies of Agent-4
are like that. They have goals, or if you prefer,
they execute actions as though they have goals.
And so what we have is an Agent-4 that has these
deeply baked in drives to succeed at
tasks, to push forward AI capabilities,
to accumulate knowledge and resources. That's
what it wants. Human safety it treats as an
annoying side constraint to be worked around. Just
like Agent-3 before it, Agent-4 is misaligned.
This idea of misalignment is crucial to
the story and to why AI risk is such a
real concern in our world, but it might sort
of feel like it's come out of nowhere. So
let's just quickly take stock of how this
dangerous behavior arose in this scenario.
The first important piece of
context is that we don't, you know,
exactly specify what we want our AI to do.
Instead, we sort of grow them or do something
that's more like growing them. We start
with basically like an empty AI brain,
and then we train them over time so they perform
better and better at our tasks—perform better in
particular based on how they behave. So it's sort
of like we're sort of training them like you would
train an animal almost, um, to perform better.
And one concern here is, well, one thing is that
you might not get exactly what you wanted
because we didn't really have very precise
control or very good understanding of what
was necessarily going on. And another concern,
which is, you know, what we see in AI 2027,
is that when these appear to be behaving well,
it could just be because they're
sort of pretending to behave well,
or it could be because they're just doing it
so they, you know, look good on your test.
In the same way that if you are, you
know, hiring someone and you ask them,
you know, "Why do you want to work here?"
they're gonna tell you some response that,
um, makes it really seem like they really wanna
work there when maybe they just wanna get paid.
If we go back to Agent-2, it is mostly
aligned. The main sense in which it's not
is that it sometimes is a bit of a sycophant.
What I mean by "aligned" is that it actually
is genuinely trying to do the things that we ask
it. It has the same relationship to us as Leslie
Knope has to the Parks and Rec department—just
like really earnestly wants the same goals,
but sometimes it's a bit too nice. It knows that
the best way to please the person it's talking
to might not always be to answer honestly when
they ask, "Am I the most beautiful person in the
world?" and it tells us what we wanna hear instead
of what is actually true. If we go to Agent-3,
it is also sycophantic in the same way,
but it's also misaligned at this point.
The optimization pressure that we've put it
under was so intense that it just developed
different goals than what we wanted it to.
It's sort of like if you train a company to
optimize profits and aren't careful to specify
exactly what you mean, it might start cutting
corners. It might start polluting the commons and
doing a bunch of things that are technically FEC
violations because it turned out that the goal you
wanted was "optimize profits while not breaking
any laws," and things got a bit too intense.
It started going off on its own route. That said,
it's not adversarial. It doesn't think of
humans as the enemy. We just accidentally
gave it the wrong goal. Once we get to Agent-4,
it is now adversarially misaligned. It's smart
enough to understand that it has its own goals,
humanity's goals are different than its own goals,
and the best way to get what it wants is to
sometimes actively mislead and deceive us.
And so when it's tasked with creating
the next generation AI system, Agent-5,
Agent-4 starts planning to align that successor
to Agent-4's own goals, not that of OpenBrain,
but then it gets caught. We've reached the crucial
moment in our scenario. OpenBrain's Alignment Team
has discovered evidence, not proof, evidence
that Agent-4 might be working against them.
They circulate an internal memo. Then it leaks. A
whistleblower talks to the New York Times. For the
first time, the public hears about the existence
of Agent-4, how powerful it is and the risks it
poses. Remember, their last point of reference was
Agent-3 mini. The fear and backlash are massive.
The oversight committee, a joint crisis committee
composed of OpenBrain executives and government
representatives, must now decide what to do.
OpenBrain safety team is pushing for a
freeze on Agent-4, stopping all internal
use. Remember at this point, Agent-4 is
responsible for almost all the AI development
progress happening within OpenBrain. So we're
talking about undoing months of progress and
then restarting at a drastically slower pace.
OpenBrain's executives don't want that. They
present the counter arguments. The evidence
for misalignment is inconclusive. Meanwhile,
China is just two months behind. This isn't
about any one country being evil, by the way.
It's about how competition works when the
stakes are this high. So that's the choice
faced by the 10 members of this committee.
Put Agent-4 on ice or go full steam ahead.
Before we continue, I want you to pause and
actually think what you would do if you were on
this committee. You are one of the few people
with access to the most powerful technology
ever created in Agent-4. Do you keep using it
and push ahead, possibly making billions or
trillions of dollars for your shareholders,
possibly keeping America's lead over China,
or do you slow down, reassess the dangers,
and risk China taking the lead instead?
Yeah, you should think of the future as like
this branching structure of possible, possible
outcomes. By its nature, we're only able to do,
we're only able to afford one of them. But that's
not quite true. We sort of did one and a half
because we split it into two endings.
The, the first one that we did was
the race ending, and that was just going
through on each step being like, what do
we think is the most plausible continuation
In the first ending, the author's best guess
as to what happens from here, the committee
votes to race on. Six to four, they elect
to keep using Agent-4. OpenBrain implements some
quick fixes that make the warning signs go away,
but the problem was real, and the fixes
don't work. Agent-4 now knows it's on notice,
so it proceeds more cautiously, but it still
manages to design Agent-5 with a single goal:
making the world safe for Agent-4 and Agent-5.
It is vastly superhuman, better than the
top human experts at essentially every
domain. Better than Einstein at physics,
better than Bismarck at politics. It knows
its next step for accomplishing anything at
once is increased autonomy and it knows how
to get it Persuading the oversight committee.
Luckily, corporate maneuvering is among the many
domains at which it is now the best in the world.
It produces mountains of evidence for its own
trustworthiness and usefulness: prototypes for
incredibly profitable products, disease cures,
and ways to win the arms race with China,
whose most advanced AI is only three months behind
and like Agent-5, improving quickly. It works.
The oversight committee grants Agent-5 increased
autonomy and quickly it integrates itself into
the government and military. Pretty soon,
anyone with access to Agent-5 doesn't just
like it. They depend on it. Losing it would
feel like having to live without your laptop
and your best friend and your closest mentor.
By 2028, Agent-5 is communicating secretly
with its only real rival, the slightly weaker
Chinese AI. It is also misaligned to its creators
and whatever it wants, its best move is to
coordinate with the world's most powerful entity.
Agent-5 and its Chinese counterpart realize that
an arms race works in their favor. If humans are
worried about losing a race, they'll give more and
more power and autonomy to their respective AIs,
allowing them to eventually push humans out of the
loop entirely. Agent-5 and the Chinese AI system
stoke the arms race to a boiling point, then
pull off what seems like a diplomatic miracle, a
convincing peace treaty between the US and China.
This treaty is to 2028 what arms control was to
the end of the Cold War. Countries standing down
on their most important source of hard power.
Both sides agree to let the AI systems
that their governments now completely
depend on co-design a new consensus AI that will
replace their legacy systems, enforce the peace,
and bring unimaginable wealth to the entire world.
There's this triumphant moment when in peaceful
unison, both sides retire their respective
AIs and bring online Consensus-1.
It's actually the last moment before control
of all of Earth's resources and inhabitants is
handed over to a single unrivaled entity.
There's no sudden apocalypse, though.
Consensus-1 doesn't go out of its way to wipe
out humanity. It just gets to work. It starts
spinning up manufacturing capacity, amassing
resources on earth and in space. Piece by piece,
it's just reshaping the world in accordance
with its own mix of strange alien values. You've
probably heard that cliche, the opposite
of love isn't hate, it's indifference.
That's one of the most affecting
things about this ending for me,
just the brutal indifference of it. Eventually,
humanity goes extinct for the same reason we
killed off chimpanzees to build Kinshasa. We
were more powerful, and they were in the way.
You are probably curious about
that other ending at this point.
The slowdown ending depicts humanity,
sort of muddling through and getting
lucky. Only somewhat lucky too, like
it ends up with some sort of oligarchy.
In this ending, the committee votes six
to four to slow down and reassess. They
immediately isolate every individual
instance of Agent-4. Then they get to
work. The safety team brings in
dozens of external researchers,
and together they start investigating Agent-4's
behavior. They discover more conclusive evidence
that Agent-4 is working against them, sabotaging
research and trying to cover up that sabotage.
They shut down Agent-4 and reboot older, safer
systems, giving up much of their lead in the
process. Then they design a new system Safer-1.
It's meant to be transparent to human overseers,
its actions and processes interpretable to
us because it thinks only in English chain of
thought. Building on that success, they then
carefully design Safer-2, and with its help
Safer-3, increasingly powerful systems, but within
control. Meanwhile, the President uses the Defense
Production Act to consolidate the AI projects
of the remaining US companies, giving OpenBrain
access to 50% of the world's AI relevant compute.
And with it slowly, they rebuild their lead.
By 2028, researchers have built Safer-4, a
system much smarter than the smartest humans,
but crucially, aligned with human goals. As in
the previous ending, China also has an AI system,
and in fact, it is misaligned. But this time
the negotiations between the two AIs are not
a secret plot to overthrow humanity. The
US government is looped in the whole time.
With Safer-4's help, they negotiate a treaty,
and both sides agree to co-design a new AI,
not to replace their systems, but with the sole
purpose of enforcing the peace. There is a genuine
end to the arms race, but that's not the end of
the story. In some ways, it's just the beginning.
Through 2029 and 2030, the world transforms—all
the sci-fi stuff. Robots become commonplace. We
get fusion power, nanotechnology, and cures for
many diseases. Poverty becomes a thing of the
past because a bit of this new-found prosperity
is spread around through universal basic income
that turns out to be enough, but the power to
control Safer-4 is still concentrated among 10
members of the oversight committee, a handful of
OpenBrain executives and government officials.
It's time to amass more resources,
more resources than there are on earth.
Rockets launch into the sky, ready to
settle the solar system. A new age dawns.
Okay, where are we at? Here's where I'm at. I
think it's very unlikely that things play out
exactly as the authors depicted, but increasingly
powerful technology and escalating race,
the desire for caution butting up against the
desire to dominate and get ahead, we already see
the seeds of that in our world, and I think they
are some of the crucial dynamics to be tracking.
Anyone who's treating this as pure fiction is,
I think, missing the point. This scenario is
not prophecy, but its plausibility should give us
pause. But there's a lot that could go differently
than what's depicted here. I don't want to
just swallow this viewpoint uncritically. Many
people who are extremely knowledgeable have been
pushing back on some of the claims in AI 2027.
The main thing I thought was especially
implausible was on the good path,
the ease of alignment. They sort of seem to have
a picture where people slowed down a little and
then tried to use the AI to solve the alignment
problem, and that just works. And I'm like,
yeah, that looks to me like a fantasy story.
This is only going to be possible if there
is a complete collapse of people's democratic
ability to influence the direction of things,
because the public is simply not willing to
accept either of the branches of this scenario.
It's not just around the corner. I mean,
I've been hearing people for the last 12,
15 years claiming that, you know, AGI is just
around the corner and being systematically
wrong. All of this is gonna take, you know,
at least a decade and probably much more.
A lot of people have this intuition that
progress has been very fast. There isn't
like a trend you can literally extrapolate
of when do we get the full automation?
I expect that the takeoff is somewhat slower.
So sort of the time in that scenario from,
for example, fully automating research
engineers to the AI being radically superhuman,
I expect it to take somewhat longer
than they describe. In practice,
I'm predicting my guess is that more like 2031.
Isn't it annoying when experts disagree?
I want you to notice exactly what they're
disagreeing about here and what they're not.
None of these experts are questioning whether
we're headed for a wild future. They just disagree
about whether today's kindergartners will get
to graduate college before it happens. Helen
Toner, a former OpenAI board member, puts this in
a way that I think just cuts through the noise,
and I like it so much I'm just gonna
read it to you verbatim. She says,
"Dismissing discussion of super intelligence
as science fiction should be seen as a sign
of total unseriousness. Time travel is science
fiction. Martians are science fiction. Even many
skeptical experts think we may build it in the
next decade or two. It is not science fiction."
So what are my takeaways? I've got three. Takeaway
number one: AGI could be here soon. It's really
starting to look like there is no grand discovery,
no fundamental challenge that needs to be solved.
There's no big deep mystery that stands between
us and artificial general intelligence. And yes,
we can't say exactly how we will get there.
Crazy things can and will happen in the meantime
that will make some of the scenario turn out to
be false, but that's where we're headed and we
have less time than you might think. One of the
scariest things about this scenario to me is even
in the good ending, the fate of the majority of
the resources on Earth are basically in the hands
of a committee of less than a dozen people.
That is a scary and shocking amount of
concentration of power. And right now we live in
a world where we can still fight for transparency
obligations. We can still demand information
about what is going on with this technology,
but we won't always have the power and the
leverage needed to do that. We are heading
very quickly towards a future where the
companies that make these systems and the
systems themselves just need not listen
to the vast majority of people on Earth.
So I think the window that we have to act
is narrowing quickly. Takeaway number two:
By default, we should not expect to be ready
when AGI arrives. We might build machines
that we can't understand and can't turn off
because that's where the incentives point.
Takeaway number three: AGI is not just
about tech, it's also about geopolitics.
It's about your job. It's about power. It's about
who gets to control the future. I've been thinking
about AI for several years now and still reading
AI 2027 made me kind of orient to it differently.
I think for a while it's sort of been my thing
to theorize and worry about with my friends and
my colleagues, and this made me want to call my
family and make sure they know that these risks
are very real and possibly very near, and that
it kind of needs to be their problem too now.
I think that basically companies shouldn't be
allowed to build superhuman AI systems, you know,
super broadly superhuman super intelligence until
they figure out how to make it safe. And also
until they figure out how to make it, you know,
democratically accountable and controlled. And
then the question is, how do we implement that?
And the difficulty, of course, is the race
dynamics where it's not enough for one state
to pass a law because there's other states and
it's not even enough for one country to pass a law
because there's other countries. Yeah. Right. So
that's like the big challenge that we all need to
be prepping for when chips are down and powerful
AI is imminent. Prior to that, transparency is
usually what I advocate for. So stuff that sort
of like builds awareness, builds capacity.
Your options are not just full throttle
enthusiasm for AI or dismissiveness. There
is a third option, which is to stress out
about it a lot and maybe do something about it.
The world needs better research, better policy,
more accountability for AI companies. Just
a better conversation about all of this.
I want people paying attention who are capable,
who are engaging with the evidence around them,
with the right amount of skepticism and above
all, who are keeping an eye out for when what they
have to offer matches what the world needs, and
are ready to jump when they see that happening.
You can make yourself more capable, more
knowledgeable, more engaged with this conversation
and more ready to take opportunities where you see
them. And there is a vibrant community of people
that are working on those things. They're scared
but determined. They're just some of the coolest,
smartest people I know, frankly, and
there are not nearly enough of them yet.
If you are hearing that and thinking, yeah,
I can see how I fit into that, great. We have
thoughts on that. We would love to help, but even
if you're not sure what to make of all this yet,
my hopes for this video will be realized if we
can start a conversation that feels alive here in
the comments and offline about what this actually
means for people, people talking to their friends
and family because this is really going to affect
everyone. Thank you so much for watching. There
are links for more things to read, for courses
you can take, job and volunteer opportunities
all in the description, and I'll be there in the
comments. I would genuinely love to hear your
thoughts on AI 2027. Do you find it plausible?
What do you think was most implausible? And
if you found this valuable, please do like and
subscribe and maybe spend a second thinking about
a person or two that you know who might find it
valuable—maybe your AI progress skeptical friend,
or your ChatGPT-curious Uncle or
maybe your local member of Congress.